Guillaume Lobet

Assistant Professor - Functional structural modelling of crop systems

Informations

28-12-1984 [33]

g.lobet@fz-juelich.de

www.guillaumelobet.be

Keywords

Computational modelling
Image analysis
Data analysis
Web technologies
Science communication
Open Science

Languages

French ★★★★ English (C1/C2) ★★★☆ Sign language ★☆☆☆☆

Note:

All my articles, presentations and projects can be viewed at www.guillaumelobet.be

Research statement

Plants are fascinating. They form complex and plastic networks (both above- and below-ground), ever integrating and adapting to endogenous and exogenous clues. Manipulation of these networks brings the promise to unlock plant productivity in limiting environments. My primary research interests lie in the understanding of these interconnected, multi-scale regulations pathways in crop plants.

The incredible complexity of plants calls for integrative research strategies such as **combining innovative plant phenotyping pipelines with powerful data analysis and modelling tools**. My belief is that combining computational tools with the latest biological knowledge will open new horizons for plant research. Which is why I spend most of my time developing new tools, connecting them to existing ones and making them available for the plant science community.

Current position

2016-now

Assistant Professor

Forschungszentrum Jülich | University of Louvain

We use and develop computational tools to understand how plants regulate their growth through long distance signals (such as water and carbon flows).

Bibliometrics

Peer-review publications: **26**Total number of citations: **596**

Total number of citations. 59

H-index: 13

Guest editor: GigaScience

Reviews performed: 58

Invitations to conferences/workshops: **15** Organisation of conferences/workshops: **3**

Academic editor: Plant Direct

Professional experiences

2016-now	Assistant Professor	Forschungszentrum Jülich University of Louvain
2014–2016	FNRS post-doctoral fellow	Plant Physiology, PhytoSYSTEMS, ULg
2013–2014	Post-doctoral fellow	Plant Physiology, PhytoSYSTEMS, ULg
2008–2012	PhD student	Ecophysiology and Plant Breeding, UCL
2010-2012	President of the ACELI	Earth and Life Insititue, UCL

Professional experiences

2014–2016 FNRS post-doctoral fellow

PhytoSYSTEMS, Univeristé de Liège, Belgium

Advisor: Prof. Claire Périlleux

Fellowship: Fonds de la Recherche Scientifique - FNRS

Understand allometric relationships in maize, both at the plant and root system level. The project combines phenotyping, modelling and transcrip-

tomic approaches.

2015-2016 FNRS post-doctoral fellow Forschungszentrum Jülich IBG-3, Germany

Advisor: Prof. Andrea Schnepf

Fellowship: Fonds de la Recherche Scientifique - FNRS

Improve an existing plant model and couple it to a soil water movement model in order to explicitly simulate water and carbon fluxes in the plant.

2013-2014 Post-doctoral fellow

PhytoSYSTEMS, Univeristé de Liège, Belgium

MARS project: www.iap-mars.be Advisor: Prof. Claire Périlleux

Fellowship: Belgian Science Policy, Inter-university Attraction Pole

Better understand how root and shoot influence each other and how this interaction contributes to the development of the plant.

2008-2012 PhD student

Earth and Life Institute, UCL, Belgium

Regulation of water flow in the soil-root domain.

Supervisor: Prof. Xavier Draye

Fellowship: FNRS-FRIA + DROPS (EU-FP7)

The objective of the thesis was to (1) analyse the water flows in the soilroot domain (2) quantify the contribution of plant regulatory processes.

President of the ACELI 2010-2012

Earth and Life Institute, UCL, Belgium

The ACELI is the Earth and Life Institute Researchers' Association. It represents more than 300 researchers from multiple fields such as agronomy, microbiology, environmental sciences or climatology.

Computational skills

Plant phenotyping

Java, ImageJ, R

Implementation of several plant image analysis tools. Integration of modelling tools within phenotyping pipelines

Plant modelling Java, R

Implementation of a functional-structural plant model, PlaNet-Maize. Creation of a model of tomato inflorescence development.

Public database creation and management

SQL, HTML5, PHP, Javascript

www.plant-image-analysis.org www.flor-id.be

Web-based tools R, HTML

MECHA: mecharoot.github.io CRootBox: bit.ly/crootbox-web ArchiDART: https://archidart.github.io

Water Tool Network: bit.ly/water-network-app

Awards, distinctions and grants

2015	Teaching Tools in Plant Biology Competition - Plant Cell Root System Architecture quantification. Why and How? Winner
2015	Roundtable organisation competition Winner Rhizosphere 4 Meeting
2014	FNRS Post-doctoral fellowship \sim 160 000 \in (3 years salary) Fonds de la Recherche Scientifique - FNRS, Belgium
2012	Honorary fellowship Belgian American Educational Fundation
2012	
2010	Best poster Plant Science Doctoral School, Liège, Belgium First prize
2010	FRIA fellowship $\sim96~000$ \in (4 years salary) Fonds de la Recherche Scientifique - FNRS, Belgium

Education

2008–2012	PhD in agronomical sciences	Ecophysiology and Plant Breeding, UCL
2012	Teaching formation for higher education	n IPM, UCL
2003–2008	Master in bio-engineering	Université catholique de Louvain
2007	Erasmus Exchange program	University of Manchester, UK

Other informations

Teaching experience

Plant-soil interactions, Root modelling, Scientific figures, LaTeX and ImageJ course

Thesis supervision

Supervision of 3 PhD (ongoing) and 6 master theses

Boy-scout leader

Organisation of projects abroad (Ireland, Czech Republic, Morocco)

Personal interests

Sign languages and deaf culture, reading, technology, running, hiking, environment

Work overview

Publications

Peer-review publications: **26** Total number of citations: **597**

H-index: 12

Guest editor: GigaScience

Reviews performed: **58**

Invitations to conferences/workshops: **15** Organisation of conferences/workshops: **3**

Academic editor: Plant Direct

- Journal names were intentionally left blank.
- Link to all articles can be found on www.guillaumelobet.be.
- Bibliometric data are coming from dimensions.ai and altmetric.com.
- The Field Citation Ratio (FCR) indicates the relative citation performance of an article, when compared to similarly-aged articles in its subject area (1 = average).
- The Altmetric Score is an automatically calculated, weighted count of all of the attention a research output has received online.

Pre-print articles

Connecting the dots between computational tools to analyse soil-root water relations

```
Passot, S., C. Couvreur, F. Meunier, X. Draye, M. Javaux, D. Leitner, L. Pagès, A. Schnepf, J. Vanderborght, and G. Lobet
```

2018 | Citation(s): | FCR: | Altmetric score: 19 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/312918

Novel multiscale insights into the composite nature of water transport in roots

```
Couvreur, V., M. Faget, G. Lobet, M. Javaux, F. Chaumont, and X. Draye 2017 | Citation(s): 1 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 10 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/147314
```

Articles in peer-reviewed journals

archiDART v3.0, A new data analysis pipeline allowing the topological analysis of plant root systems

```
Delory, B. and M. Li
2018 | Citation(s): 2 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 36
URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.12688/f1000research.13541.1
```

Impact of crop residue management on crop production and soil chemistry after seven years of crop rotation in temperate climate, loamy soils

```
Hiel, M., S. Barbieux, J. Pierreux, C. Olivier, G. Lobet, C. Roisin, S. Garré, G. Colinet, B. Bodson, and B. Dumont

2018 | Citation(s): - | FCR: - | Altmetric score: 2

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/peerj.4836
```

Measuring root system traits of wheat in 2D images to parameterize 3D root architecture models

```
Landl, M., A. Schnepf, J. Vanderborght, G. Bengough, S. Bauke, G. Lobet, R. Bol, and H. Vereecken 2018 | Citation(s): | FCR: | Altmetric score: 
. URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11104-018-3595-8
```

A spatio-temporal analysis of early root system development reveals three types of lateral roots

```
Passot, S., B. Moreno-Ortega, D. Moukouanga, C. Balsera, S. GUYOMARC'H, M. Lucas, G. Lobet, L. Laplaze, B. Muller, and Y. Guédon 2018 | Citation(s): | FCR: | Altmetric score: 24 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1104/pp.17.01648
```

CRootBox, A Structural-Functional Modelling Framework For Root Systems

```
Schnepf, A., D. Leitner, M. Landl, G. Lobet, T. Hieu Mai, S. Morandage, C. Sheng, M. Zoerner, J. Vanderborght, and H. Vereecken 2018 | Citation(s): 2 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 70 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/aob/mcx221
```

Combining semi-automated image analysis techniques with machine learning algorithms to accelerate large scale genetic studies

```
Atkinson, J., G. Lobet, M. Noll, P. Meyer, M. Griffiths, and D. Wells 2017 | Citation(s): 4 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 43 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29020748
```

Image analysis in plant science. Publish then perish

```
Lobet, G.
2017 | Citation(s): 13 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 50
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28571940
```

This is a timely article, and one which correctly characterises key issues facing those creating and using image analysis tools in the biological sciences. The data presented is interesting and informative, and biologists using image analysis tools should be made aware of the issues raised in this paper.

[Anonymous Reviewer 2]

Using a structural root system model to evaluate and improve the accuracy of root image analysis pipelines

```
Lobet, G., T. Koevoets I, P. Tocquin, L. Pagès, and C. Périlleux 2017 | Citation(s): 8 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 72 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28421089
```

An evaluation of inexpensive methods for root image acquisition when using rhizotrons

```
Mohamed, A., Y. Monnier, G. Lobet, J.-L. Maeght, M. Ramel, and A. Stokes 2017 | Citation(s): 3 | FCR: | Altmetric score: - URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28286541
```

Teaching Tools in Plant Biology, Phenomics of root system architecture

```
2017 | Citation(s): 1 | FCR: | Altmetric score: 18
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29018159
```

Integrating roots into a whole plant network of flowering time genes in Arabidopsis thaliana

```
Bouché, F., M. D Alioa, P. Tocquin, G. Lobet, N. Detry, and C. Périlleux 2016 | Citation(s): 4 | FCR: 1.65 | Altmetric score: 9 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/27352932
```

Environmental Control of Root System Biology

```
Rellan-Alvarez, R., G. Lobet, and J. Dinneny
2016 | Citation(s): 22 | FCR: 8.65 | Altmetric score: 8
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26905656
```

FLOR-ID, an interactive database of flowering-time gene networks in Arabidopsis thaliana

```
Bouché, F. and G. Lobet
2015 | Citation(s): 23 | FCR: 8.53 | Altmetric score: 31
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26476447
```

F1000 Recommended: FLOR-ID presents an impressive effort in bringing together literature on flowering-time regulation in Arabidopsis. Pathways are presented as interconnected schemes with

the possibility of accessing individual gene information such as mutant phenotype or post-translational regulation. Every scheme presents data in a very explicit way, making this database ideal for newcomers to the field or for teaching.

[F. Parcy, CNRS]

archiDART, an R package for the automated 2D computation of plant root architectural traits

Delory, B., C. Baudson, Y. Brostaux, G. Lobet, and P. du Jardin 2015 | Citation(s): 6 | FCR: 4.91 | Altmetric score: 24 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11104-015-2673-4

Root System Markup Language. Toward an unified root architecture description language

Lobet, G., M. Pound, J. Diener, C. Pradal, X. Draye, C. Godin, M. Javaux, D. Leitner, F. Meunier, and P. Nacry

2015 | Citation(s): 31 | FCR: 16.5 | Altmetric score: 34 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25614065

It is clear that the language will help empower plant biologists and computation scientist working in root phenotyping and modeling fields to leverage and share work more efficiently with others.

[Anonymous Reviewer 2]

Rhizoponics, a novel hydroponic rhizotron for root system analyses on mature Arabidopsis thaliana plants

```
Mathieu, L. and G. Lobet
2015 | Citation(s): 16 | FCR: 4.21 | Altmetric score: 4
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25657812
```

GLO-Roots, an imaging platform enabling multidimensional characterization of soil grown root systems

Rellán-Álvarez, R., G. Lobet, H. Hildner, P. Pradier, J. Sebastian, C. Yee, G. Yu, T. LaRue, C. Trontin, and R. Nieu

2015 | Citation(s): 43 | FCR: 16.01 | Altmetric score: 120 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26287479

Comparative analysis of Cd and Zn impacts on root distribution and morphology of Lolium perenne and Trifolium repens. Implications for phytostabilization

```
Lambrechts, T., G. Lequeue, G. Lobet, and B. Godin
2014 | Citation(s): 6 | FCR: 1.27 | Altmetric score: -
URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11104-013-1975-7
```

A modeling approach to determine the importance of dynamic regulation of plant hydraulic conductivities on the water uptake dynamics in the soil-plant-atmosphere system

```
Lobet, G.
2014 | Citation(s): 8 | FCR: 1.69 | Altmetric score: 1
URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2013.11.025
```

Plant Water Uptake in Drying Soils

```
Lobet, G., C. Couvreur, and F. Meunier
2014 | Citation(s): 34 | FCR: 7.47 | Altmetric score: 3
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24515834
```

In summary, the update delivers a very useful overview of this complex, fast moving multidisciplinary area, that will be invaluable to non-specialists and specialists alike.

[Anonymous Reviewer 2]

Inflorescence development in tomato, gene functions within a zigzag model

```
Périlleux, C.
2014 | Citation(s): 15 | FCR: 2.74 | Altmetric score: 3
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24744766
```

Root systems biology, integrative modeling across scales, from gene regulatory networks to the rhizosphere

Hill, K., S. Porco, G. Lobet, S. Zappala, and S. Mooney

```
2013 | Citation(s): 20 | FCR: 2.55 | Altmetric score: 4 URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24143806
```

An online database for plant image analysis software tools

```
Lobet, G.
2013 | Citation(s): 72 | FCR: 29.86 | Altmetric score: 36
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24107223
```

The database has a visiting rate of 10 000 page views / month

Guillaume did the community of plant biologists a huge favor by creating a webpage that describes and links to a large number of image analysis tools that have been designed to solve a measurement problem in plant biology. Nobody knows more about what's already out there than Guillaume.

[E. Spalding, University of Madison]

Novel scanning procedure enabling the vectorization of entire rhizotron-grown root systems

```
2013 | Citation(s): 46 | FCR: 7.88 | Altmetric score: URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/23286457
```

A novel image-analysis toolbox enabling quantitative analysis of root system architecture

```
Lobet, G.
2011 | Citation(s): 133 | FCR: 49.84 | Altmetric score: 3
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21771915
```

Model-assisted integration of physiological and environmental constraints affecting the dynamic and spatial patterns of root water uptake from soils

```
Draye, X. and Y. Kim
2010 | Citation(s): 84 | FCR: 9.66 | Altmetric score: -
URL: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20453027
```

Invited presentations in international conferences

Alternative plants, why we need models to understand the complexity of plants

```
CRAG Seminar, Barcelona, Spain, 2018
URL: https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.6188372.v1
```

Non-linear plant phenotyping pipelines. How can structural models and machine learning can help us analyse large plant image datasets

```
Phenome 2018, Tucson, USA, 2018
URL: https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5885329.v2
```

Alternative plants, why we need models to understand the complexity of plants

```
IPG Symposium, Missouri, USA, 2017
URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5089900.v1
```

Using machine learning and growth models to streamline large scale root phenotyping

```
JST International Workshop on Field Phenotyping, Tokyo, Japan, 2017 URL: https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.5682775.v1
```

Open Science. A view from the Bench

```
Open Belgium Conference, Antwerpen, Belgium, 2016
URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3020170
```

Introducing Root System Markup Language

Modeling plant development from the organ to the whole plant scale, Montpellier, France, 2015 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1379862

Plant Image Analysis tools. Current trends and limitations

Plant Image Analysis Problems and Solution, Madison, Wisconsin, 2015

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1169928

Science Valorisation

Communiquer sa recherche, Brussels, Belgium, 2015

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1057995

Science Valorisation

Let's Talk Science, Leuven, Belgium, 2015

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1057995

Structural Root Modelling

Winter School on Root Phenotyping, Jülich, Germany, 2015

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1594792

Modelling water relations in the soil-plant-atmosphere system

SEB Main Meeting, Manchester, UK, 2014

URL: http://figshare.com/articles/Modelling_water_relations_in_the_soil_plant_atmosphere_system/1091425

Water relations in the soil-plant system. What can we learn from functional-structural plant models

BASF Top Science Meeting, Mannheim, Germany, 2014

URL: http://figshare.com/articles/Modelling_water_relations_in_the_soil_plant_atmosphere_system/1091425

Water relations in the SPAC. What can we learn from functional-structural plant models

Soil Science Society Belgium, Brussels, Belgium, 2014

URL: http://figshare.com/articles/Modelling_water_relations_in_the_soil_plant_atmosphere_system/1091425

A Novel Image Analysis Toolbox Enabling Quantitative Analysis of Root System Architecture.

International Workshop on Image Analysis Methods for Plant Science, Nottingham, UK, 2012 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.95665

New insights on the role of root radial conductivity on the overall uptake dynamics

Roots for improving resource acquisition in crops, Grasmere, UK, 2011

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.95591

Presentations in international conferences

How to deal with the complexity of plants, a modelling vision

CPIB Seminar, Nottingham, UK, 2016

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4239140.v3

plant-image-analysis.org, A platform referencing plant image analysis tools

Neubias Taggathon, Barcelona, Spain (video-conference), 2016

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.3826488

Using structural models to validate and improve root image analysis pipelines

International Plant Phenotyping Symposium, Mexico City, Mexico, 2016

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4311848.v1

FLOR-ID, an interactive database of flowering gene network in Arabidopsis

Workshop on Mechanisms Controling Flower Development, Aiguablava, Spain, 2015 URL: http://orbi.ulg.ac.be/handle/2268/180776

Inflorescence development in tomato. Gene functions within a zigzag model.

Genetic Variation of Flowering Time Genes and Applications for Crop Improvement, Bielefeld, Germany, 2014

URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.976039

Plant Image Analysis tools. Current trends and limitations

International workshop on Image analysis methods for the plant sciences, Aberythwyth, UK, 2014 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.1169928

First steps towards an explicit modeling of aba production and translocation in relation with the water uptake dynamics

9th International Workshop on Sap Flow, Ghent, Belgium, 2013 URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.713568